<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Novemb. 18. 1642. The unlimited prerogative of kings subverted. Or a short treatise grounded upon scripture and reason, to prove that kings ought as well as others to bee accountable for their actions. By a well wisher to the church of God, his King and countrey. And dedicated to all such as love the truth.</title>
            <author>Well wisher to the Church of God, his King and countrey.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95803</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing U84</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E127_32</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16462</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860037</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860037</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156215</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95803)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156215)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 22:E127[32])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Novemb. 18. 1642. The unlimited prerogative of kings subverted. Or a short treatise grounded upon scripture and reason, to prove that kings ought as well as others to bee accountable for their actions. By a well wisher to the church of God, his King and countrey. And dedicated to all such as love the truth.</title>
                  <author>Well wisher to the Church of God, his King and countrey.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 21 1642".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Duties --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:156215:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156215:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The unlimited PREROGATIVE OF KINGS ſubverted. Or a Short <hi>Treatiſe</hi> grounded upon <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> to prove that <hi>Kings</hi> ought as well as others to bee accountable for their Actions.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATTHEW 22.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Render unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and unto God the things that are Gods.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>By a well wiſher to the Church of God, His King and <hi>Countrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And dedicated to all ſuch as love the Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THere will be times</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>wherein men will not indure ſound doctrine,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.3. <hi>but will give heed to ſeduceing ſpirits, and doctrines of devils.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly if ever theſe times ſhall come to be fullfilled, now they are, when as Court Paraſites and ambitious flatterers, Divines as well as others whoſe chiefeſt Policy now it is to <hi>have mens perſons in admiration for advantage ſake, Iude</hi> 16. and to pleaſe thoſe by whom they may be dignified or rewarded; care not what falſities they ſpeak, nor what untruths they doe maintain; and which is worſt of all, are not aſham'd to father their lies even upon the very Scriptures of truth themſelves, <hi>wreſting the ſame</hi> (as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. through their willingly wilfull Ignorance) <hi>to their own deſtruction.</hi> Among which this is none of the leaſt, which they ſay, <hi>That Kings are not reſponſall to any, ſave God for their actions:</hi> And for this they bring the ſaying of the Preacher, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.4 where he ſaith thus, <hi>Where the word of a King is there is power, and who may ſay unto him what doeſt thou?</hi> Which words if they be throughly ſcan'd and examined, you ſhall find they yeeld no ſuch conſtruction; but rather the contrary: For in the 2d verſe before going, the Wiſe man gives us this charge <hi>to keep the Kings Commandement.</hi> I ſuppoſe, if they underſtand themſelvs they will not ſay that by vertue therof we are bound to do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the King injoynes us, whether it be right or wrong: but that it hath reſpect to thoſe things that are either agreeable, or at leaſt not contrary to the Commandement of God; and the reaſon therof is given in the words following in regard of the Oath of God. Now there are none (I think) will ſay (if Kings come lawfully in with the choice and conſent of their People, as all lawfull Kings doe) that his Oath hath only reſpect unto the People, as if it did bind only on their part; but alſo on the part of the King, who Sweares to rule and govern them according to the Laws of God, and of
<pb facs="tcp:156215:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Land; and upon this condition they Sweare Obedience unto him. This we may ſee ſufficiently proved by the Covenant of <hi>David</hi> made with his people, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.1. where it is ſaid. <hi>All the Elders of Iſrael came to the King to Hebron, and</hi> David <hi>made a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with them in Hebron before the Lord:</hi> and then it followes, <hi>they anointed him King over Iſrael.</hi> And then again wee ſee this proved by the mutuall Oath between <hi>Ioaſh</hi> and his people, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23.11. where it is ſaid, <hi>they brought out the Kings Son and put upon him the Crown, and gave him the Teſtimonie</hi> (that is to ſay) they made him enter into this Covenant to keep the Law of God, and to Govern them according thereunto: and then it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, <hi>they made him King, and Iehojada and his Sons anointed him, and ſaid, God ſave the King.</hi> And ſo again in the 16. v. of the ſame chapter. By this you ſee here was an Oath aſwell on the Kings part as on the peoples; and thus the people are bound to keep the Kings commandement, when he walks according to this rule. And ſuch is the Oath of the Kings of <hi>England</hi> when they come to their Crowns and Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>Then he ſaith further in the 3d verſe, <hi>Be not haſtie to g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e out of his ſight, ſtand not in an evill thing, for he doth whatſoever he pleaſeth.</hi> I hope there are none that dare be ſo Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiouſly bold as from theſe words to attribute unto Kings an Almighty power as the words ſeem to import, which is an Attribute only proper unto God to be Almighty, as the Pſalmiſt ſhews. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.3. <hi>Our God is in the heavens, he hath done whatſoever he pleaſed:</hi> And <hi>Pſal</hi> 135.6 <hi>Whatſoever the Lord pleaſed that did he in heaven and in earth</hi> &amp;c. This were in an high meaſure to rob God of his glory and to give that to the creature that is only due to the Creatour. Yet I know no reaſon why they may not ſay from theſe words <hi>(The King doth whatſoever he pleaſeth)</hi> that Kings have an Almighty power; as well as to ſay from the other words <hi>(who may ſay unto him what doſt thou?)</hi> that therfore Kings are accountable to none ſave God for their actions. For you ſee how the words follow one another, and what may be ſaid of Kings in one reſpect, may be ſaid of them in the other. But we may (if we will at leaſt) take notice that theſe words are brought in as having relation to <hi>good</hi> or <hi>evill;</hi> and that this is a phraſe applyed unto Kings, only to ſhew that their Power is great, and of a large extent. <hi>For the good of thoſe that doe well, and for the puniſhment of thoſe that doe evill;</hi> and that in reſpect thereof, we ſhould have an awfull and reverentiall regard of them; for ſo the words run, <hi>Stand not in an evill thing, for he doth whatſoever he pleaſeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then for the words following, which are quoted by thoſe that ſtand for the unlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Prerogative<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they have reſpect alſo to the ſame. And ſo it is moſt true, <hi>That where the word of a King is there is power:</hi> If ſpeaking as a King ſhould, performing the Office of a King; having reſpect to his Oath and Covenant between God and his people, in commanding thoſe things that are <hi>good,</hi> and puniſhing thoſe things that are <hi>evill,</hi> then indeed <hi>who may ſay unto him what doſt thou?</hi> no man may call him to Queſtion: for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as God the King of Kings hath put this power into his hands. And what is that indeed that makes Kings many times ſo ſlighted, and ſo little feared of their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple but this that they take no care at all to govern them according to their Laws? and what is it on the other ſide that addes majeſtie and magnificence unto them, but this, that they make the Laws of God and of the Land the rules of Magiſtracie and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Herein conſiſts the power of Kings, which the Wiſe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n here ſo much ſpeaks of. But now that this place is not ſo to be underſtood, as the Royaliſts of our times for their own ends would have it <hi>that Kings are n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t accountable unto men for their actions,</hi> may eaſilie appeare, by comparing this place with that in <hi>Dan.</hi> 4 35. where <hi>Nebucadnezzar</hi> after that he was reſtored again to his ſences, and to his Kingdom, makes this acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement
<pb facs="tcp:156215:2"/>concerning the power of God <hi>(Who may ſay unto him what doſt thou?)</hi> Imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus much, that howſoever Kings may be great, and their power may reach very farre, as he for his own part was none of the meaneſt, being the greateſt Monarch that was then in the world yet this did not belong unto him nor unto any King elſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever but was Gods ſole Prerogative only to be reſponſall unto none for his actions.</p>
            <p>By this you ſee how weak this place is for their purpoſe, who from hence would prove Kings <hi>unlimited power,</hi> as unaccountable to any ſave God: whereas all that the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe man aimes at, is nothing but this, to ſhew the extent of the power of Kings for their peoples good, as by their Oaths they are tyed by all lawfull wayes to advance it; and withall to ſignifie unto us, what an awfull regard we ought to have of Kings, whom God hath inveſted with ſuch a power.</p>
            <p>I: But ſay they Kings are Gods, and therfore are not accountable for any actions they doe, and the Scripture calls them ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is true the Scripture doth ſo: yet none I beleeve will be ſo blaſphemous as to ſay they are <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> ſuch as have an infinite being of and from themſelves from all eternity: They will at moſt confeſſe them to be but <hi>Elohim,</hi> and this name of God is communicable, and is oftentimes in Scripture applyed unto other creatures, both An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Men; yet not to ſuch Men only as have Kingly dignity, but unto all Rulers and Governours whatſoever: as we may ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.1. where it is ſaid, <hi>God ſtands in the Congregation of the mighty, he judgeth among the Gods.</hi> And in the words following, the Pſalmiſt incites, and ſtirres them up to the performance of their duties, in their place ſaying <hi>How long will ye judge unjuſtly, and accept the perſons of the wicked; defend the poore and fatherl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe, doe juſtice to the affli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted and needy, deliver the poore and needie, rid them out of the hand of the wicked.</hi> Then in the 6. verſe againe he ſaith, <hi>I have ſaid ye are gods</hi> &amp;c. In all this here we ſee there is not a word ſpoken of Kings in particular, but generally this phraſe is applyed unto all Rulers and Magiſtrates whatſoever: and beſides we know that the duties before ſpoken of, are proper to them as well as unto Kings. Moreover, I doe not know in all the Scriptures, where this word <hi>Elohim</hi> is ſo particularly applyed unto Kings as it ſo be in regard thereof, they ſhould be leſſe accountable for their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then any other Rulers. So then if this be true, as we plainly out of Scripture ſee it is that other Rulers as well as Kings are called Gods, then Kings as well as other Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers are accountable for their actions unleſſe that we will ſay that all Rulers and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours whatſoever are not accountable unto men for what they doe.</p>
            <p>But ſay they Kings are the <hi>higheſt powers</hi> on earth how then can they be accountable unto thoſe that are inferiour and under them, which is not accidentall unto other Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and Governours becauſe there are higher above them that they may give accompt unto: but none are above Kings: therfore they are to give accompt to none, ſave only God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ</hi> I deny that Kings on earth are the <hi>higheſt powers,</hi> and this I ſay, that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is above the King, and ſo conſequently the repreſentative body therof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the whole power of all the body of the people of the Land, being by generall conſent tranſmitted over unto it; and I prove it thus: The <hi>end</hi> is alwayes greater then the <hi>meanes,</hi> or the <hi>meanes</hi> are ſubordinate to the <hi>end,</hi> and therfore muſt needs be inferiour, for the <hi>meanes</hi> could never have bin but for ſuch or ſuch an <hi>end</hi> for which they were appointed: no wiſe man that underſtands what he ſaith will deny, but that the <hi>cauſe</hi> is <hi>greater</hi> then the <hi>effect:</hi> but Kings were ordained for this <hi>end;</hi> they were choſen and appointed both by God and Man, to be a <hi>meanes</hi> for procuring of the good and welfare of their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes,
<pb facs="tcp:156215:3"/>and had there bin no people, there had bin no Kings: by which it appeares, that Kings have their dependance upon their People, and that they were the primary <hi>cauſe,</hi> and Kings but the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>effects</hi> proceeding from them: therfore their Kingdomes are <hi>greater</hi> then they; and ſo conſequently the repreſentative bodies therof. And ſurely there is ſomwhat in it too, that Kings are call'd the Miniſters and Servants of the State, and ſo all good Kings and Governours have acknowledged themſelves to be.</p>
            <p>Then againe Kings are but the <hi>ordinance of Man,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſhews, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Submit you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme.</hi> Where the Apoſtle gives us this exhortation, to ſubmit to Kings though they be the ordinance of man. How will any ſay that they which doe infuſe a power into others are inferiour unto them into whom they doe infuſe it; that the power electing is inferiour to the power elected; that the originall is inferiour to the conſequence; that the fountain head is inferiour to the ſtreams that flow from it? I beleeve there are none that are in their right ſences will ſay it. So then, if the people are the originall of that power that is in Kings, and that the power they have is borrowed from them, as the ſtreams ſlow from the Fountain, let any judge whether is greater the King or his people. Not any particular perſon among the people nor any particular Corporations or Aſſemblies therof but the whole body of the people I ſay conſidered together; of thoſe that by eſpeciall conſent of all the people do repreſent the whole.</p>
            <p>But here it may be ſaid, How ſay you that Kings are the <hi>ordinance of man,</hi> doth not the Apoſtle once and againe <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, &amp;c. call all Rulers, and ſo conſequently Kings <hi>the ordinance of God? Let every ſoule be ſubject to the higher powers, for there is no power but of God, the powers that be are ordained of God: Whoſoever therfore reſiſteth the power reſiſteth the ordinance of God,</hi> &amp;c. If they be the ordinance of God, how be they the ordinance of Men then?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw</hi> Here give me leave to aske one Queſtion: Say any Politie or State chuſe any kind of Government, whether Kings, or Dukes or Judges, or the like, and by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall conſent for the good of the people they eſtabliſh it by Law, is not this then a <hi>humane ordinance,</hi> this or that kind of Government that they have choſen; yet I ſuppoſe you will not deny but that this is the <hi>ordinance of God,</hi> that now they ſhould ſubmit themſelvs thereto? Therfore the Apoſtle ſpeaking concerning Magiſtrates in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. ſaith not a word concerning Kings, as if they were more a divine Ordinance then other Rulers, but in generall terms he ſaith, <hi>that all rulers whatſoever are of God:</hi> But when he comes to ſpeak of Kings in particular, as he doth 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. he calls them the <hi>ordinance of man,</hi> wherby he doth as it were comment upon, and explain the meaning of thoſe words of S. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 13 as if he ſhould have ſaid thus: It is true, Power, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracie and Government <hi>is the ordinance of God,</hi> and by divine inſtitution: but ſo are not Kings, nor this nor that nor any other kind of government they are of man, and through his appointment. So that I ſay Kings, for their kind of government, are the ordinance of man: For God hath not tied any people in his Word, that they ſhall be governed by Kings, or by Dukes, or by Judges, or Eſtates or the like, but referres that unto themſelvs for their choice, according as they ſhall ſee moſt convenient for their good and proſperity; but when this or that kind of government is ordained and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by generall conſent of the people, this is <hi>the ordinance of God,</hi> which the Apoſtle gives a charge, <hi>that every one be ſubject unto</hi> (according to the old ſaying, <hi>Vox Populi vox Dei.</hi> The voice of the people is Gods voice) <hi>which they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelvs damnation.</hi> So that ſtill you ſee there is a power on earth above Kings (as I ſaid before)
<pb facs="tcp:156215:3"/>which lies in the generallity of the people, from whence they doe receive as from their Fountain head their Soveraignty and Kingly dignitie.</p>
            <p>Now then from what hath bin ſaid, followes this conſequence of neceſſitie, that if there be a greater power on earth then Kings are, Then Kings are accountable for their actions therunto, and ought to be ſubject as well as others, as appeares by that in <hi>Rom</hi> 13 1. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher powers, for there is no power but of</hi> God, <hi>the powers that be are ordained of</hi> God &amp;c. <hi>Whoſoever therfore reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordinance of</hi> God, <hi>and they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves damnation.</hi> In which words we ſee the Apoſtle gives a generall charge to all inferiours to ſubmit themſelves to their ſuperiours: therfore if Kings be inferiour to their Kingdomes, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to the repreſentative bodies therof; then Kings ought by vertue of this charge, to be ſubject thereunto as well as others.</p>
            <p>But how ought they to ſubmit what? in doing only and in matter of obedience, are they diſcharged there, ſo as though they abuſe their power never ſo exorbitantly, to ſpoile oppreſſe and deſtroy their people, cenſure may not paſſe upon them nor puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be inflicted? ſurely I find no ſuch diſtinction in all the word of God: Nay, we are commanded the contrary, and the law of nature teacheth us as much, that if there be a feſtred and a gangreen'd member in the body, that would deſtroy the whole, to cut it off for the preſervation of the whoſe.</p>
            <p>I, it is true will they ſay, if there be any feſtred or corrupted member in the body that would deſtroy the whole we ought to cut it off, rather then to ſuffer all the body to periſh, the Law of God and nature teacheth us thus much: but in caſe the head ſhould have any Gangreene in it, and you cut that off, you doe immediatly deſtroy the body; the life can not be preſerved when the Head is gone. So in like manner the King he is the Head of the State, and in that reſpect he hath ſuch an influence upon the State, that if you cut Him off, you deſtroy the whole State together with Him, as you deſtroy the body when you take away the head therof: therfore be he never ſo wicked, He is to be ſuffered and borne withall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This ſimilitude or reſemblance here doth not hold good, therfore we muſt diſtinguiſh between a naturall head, and a civill head: for if the naturall head of the body of man be taken away, the body dies: but it is not ſo with the civill Head of the State, as experience doth ſufficiently ſhew by the death of Kings. But if it were poſſible in the body of man, when one head is taken away to find another to put in his place, and ſo to preſerve the life as it may be done in the State, ſurely Heads would oftentimes be changed, and cut off as well as other members. So that if we will thus reaſon, that the Head of the State ſhould be in reſpect of His body, as the head of man in reſpect of the body of man, then it doth neceſſarily follow, that the Head being dead, the body ſhould die alſo, as is manifeſt in the body of man. But it doth not hold ſo in the head of the State as it doth in the head of the body of man, that if the head of the State be cut off the State dies, as doth the body of man: therfore the King who is the Head of the State, if a corrupted and a feſtred Member, that may indanger the deſtruction of the body of the State, ought to be cut off, for the preſervation of the whole, for, <hi>Salus populi ſuprena lex:</hi> nothing ought to be ſo much regarded as the Peoples ſafety, which is the end of all Law and government whatſoever.</p>
            <p>This ſimilitude, though it hold not good as it is above propoſed, yet it doth in the contrary, that if a King by his wicked and Tyrannicall courſes, doth deſtroy his Kingdome, he doth deſtroy himſelfe, as when the naturall body is deſtroyed, the head of neceſſity muſt periſh with it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:156215:4"/>
            <p>I but will ſome ſay this is ſtrange, Where in all the Scripture doe you find that the people have with Gods likeing and approbation ſo much as reſiſted their Kings, how much leſſe cenſured them, or brought them to tryall or puniſhment, for any actions that ever they have done?</p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe I Anſwer, that Kings in their wicked and ungodly courſes have bin reſiſted by their people, the Spirit of God ſpeaking by way of commendation of them for it, or at leaſt wiſe not diſapproving the ſame. This is evident by divers places of Scripture; As firſt of all we have an example hereof in <hi>Ionathans</hi> caſe. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14 44. where becauſe that <hi>lonathan</hi> had eaten a little Honey, contrary to the Commandement of his Father <hi>Saul,</hi> who was then King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> he would have put him to death; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the people ſtand up in his juſt defence, againſt <hi>Saul</hi> his Father, ſaying. <hi>Shall Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than die who hath wrought this great ſalvation in Iſrael,</hi> God <hi>forbid, as the Lord lives there ſhall not one haire of his head fall to the ground, for he hath wrought with</hi> God <hi>this day.</hi> Then it followes, <hi>the people reſcued Ionathan that he died not.</hi> Did they not think you reſiſt <hi>Saul,</hi> when the people reſcued him out of his hand whether he would or no, and contrary to the Oath that he had ſworne?</p>
            <p>Secondly, we have the example of <hi>David</hi> in <hi>Keilah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.7 &amp;c. where <hi>David</hi> being at <hi>Keilah,</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> hearing of it, thought he had got now his oportunity to take him, that he might kill him, as oftentimes he had before indeavoured: but it ſo pleaſed God that this came to <hi>Davids</hi> eares, that <hi>Saul</hi> ſecretly practiſed miſchief againſt him, to come and take away his life. Hereupon <hi>David</hi> inquires of God, Firſt to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were ſo or no, as that <hi>Saul</hi> would come down to <hi>Keilah?</hi> God anſwers him, that he would. Therupon the ſecond time he asks him <hi>Whether the men of Keilah would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him and his men into the hand of Saul, or no?</hi> God anſwers him that he would deliver him up. By this laſt it doth clearly appeare, that if ſo be the Keilites would have bin true to <hi>David,</hi> and have ſtood to him, he would have maintained the Town againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> and have defended himſelfe in it: otherwiſe, why ſhould <hi>David</hi> aske God the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time, <hi>Whether the men of Keilah would deliver him up and his men into the hands of Saul, or no?</hi> he might have gone his way, when that he heard <hi>Saul</hi> would come down, without asking any more queſtions, unleſſe we will ſay that the ſecond queſtion, which <hi>David</hi> propounded to aske of God, was frivolous and vaine, and ſo conſequently the anſwer that God gave it; which I ſuppoſe there are none will be ſo bold as to affirme. (This was the very caſe of Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> in <hi>Hull,</hi> who for this very action His Majeſtie was pleaſed to Proclaime him Traytor.)</p>
            <p>Then againe, it may be further ſaid of <hi>David,</hi> if he had not had a purpoſe to have reſiſted <hi>Saul</hi> in caſe of exigency, and extremity, what did he with 600. men about him? he might have fled from <hi>Saul</hi> when he was coming towards him, without ſuch a train and guard of men attending him, and ſo have ſaved himſelfe without them. Nay, he might in all probability have eſcaped his hands better, for had he not had ſo many with him, he might have kept himſelfe the more cloſe, and ſecret, ſo that he could not have bin ſo eaſily diſcovered. And beſides this we read 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.22. that <hi>There came to David to help him before Sauls death an hoaſt, like the hoaſt of</hi> God: and what? was all this preparation and aſſiſtance for nothing?</p>
            <p>One more example I will bring out of the Scriptures, and that is of King <hi>Vzziah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26 16. who incroached upon the Office of the Prieſts, and would take upon him to offer Incenſe in the Temple of the Lord, contrary to the expreſſe commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God: whereupon it is ſaid in the 17. verſe, that <hi>Azariah the Prieſt went in after
<pb facs="tcp:156215:4"/>him, and with him foureſcore Prieſts of the Lord, that were valiant men, and they withſtood Vzzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah the King, and ſaid unto him, it pertaineth not to thee Vzziah to burn Incenſe unto the Lord, but to the Prieſts the ſons of Aaron, that are conſecrated to burn incenſe; goe out of the Sanctuary, for thou haſt treſpaſsed, neither ſhall it be for thine honour from the Lord God. Then Vzziah was wroth, and had a Cenſour in his hand to burn Incenſe: and while he was wroth with the Prieſts, the Leproſie even roſe upon his forehead, before the Prieſts in the houſe of the Lord, beſides the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe altar. Then Azariah the chief Prieſt, and all the Prieſts looking upon him, and beholding that he was leprous in his forehead, thruſt him out from thence.</hi> If this be not reſiſtance, I know not what is.</p>
            <p>Beſides all this, the more to ſtoppe the mouthes of ſuch ill affected perſons in our times, that will take upon them to make much more of Kings, then ever God made or did intend there are examples even in the Primitive times among the Chriſtians, who have reſiſted their Kings in their ſinfull and unlawfull actions. As to inſtance in <hi>Lyci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> the Emperour who had granted to the Chriſtians to injoy their Religion, yet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards turning perſecutor, they ſent for <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great to aſſiſt them againſt him, and overthrew him. And againe being perſecuted by the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſent for <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperour to help them againſt him. And I doubt not but if the Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories of thoſe times were ſearched there might more examples of this nature be found out.</p>
            <p>But beſides all this, we have ſeen and known the like in our own times, as lately in the Scots, whom the King himſelfe, that now is, acquitted, when he came to a right underſtanding. So the Proteſtants in <hi>France, England</hi> all Queen <hi>Elizabeths dayes did help</hi> them. In our dayes again in King <hi>Charles</hi> his own reigne, we ſent over a great Force, in ſhew at leaſt, to help <hi>Rochel</hi> againſt the King of <hi>France.</hi> So in High <hi>Iermanie.</hi> the Princes there maintain their right againſt <hi>Charles</hi> the 5, and were helped by <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England.</hi> In the <hi>Neather-Lands</hi> it is evident from the beginning. Now ſhall we take upon us to condemn all theſe Churches for ſo doing?</p>
            <p>Then for the ſecond, which is the principall point here in diſpute, Whether Kings in caſe they doe Tyrannize over their People Oppreſſe, Spoile and Deſtroy their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and doe other ſuch like wicked and unnaturall actions may have Cenſure and Puniſhment inflicted upon them, according to the nature of their ſeverall Offences? They ſay where is there any example or expreſſe command in Scripture for this?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true, there are no examples, or Commands in Scripture for this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar caſe, or at leaſt not as I know of; yet that matters not, ſo long as we have a rule to walk by, and Commands in generall that reach to all particulars. And for this the like may very well be ſaid, as may for Parents murthering of their Children, there is no direct Law ſet down, either divine or humane, for the puniſhment of ſuch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the thing is ſo deteſtable and contrary to very nature, that it may be conceived, that there would be none ſuch found: but if there be, there are generall Laws in force for their cenſure and puniſhment, as in caſe of Murther; and by how much the nearer the relation is, the greater being the bond and tye for procuring the peace and welfare of ſuch and ſuch parties, ſo much the greater is the offence, and ſo much the more liable are they to puniſhment. So I ſay though there are no particular Laws ſet down, for the correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and puniſhing of ſuch Kings and Princes as doe Oppreſſe Spoil and Deſtroy their People, yet ſo much is included in thoſe generall Laws both of God and Man; and ſo much the more liable are they to Cenſure and puniſhment, by how much they are Ordained, to be greater inſtruments of the good and well being of their People then
<pb facs="tcp:156215:5"/>others are. (For this is the very nature and being of a King. He is ſuch a one as <hi>cares</hi> and <hi>provides</hi> for the Common vealth, takes <hi>pleaſure</hi> in the <hi>commodity</hi> and <hi>profit</hi> of His Subjects; and in all his doings hath reſpect to the <hi>proſperity</hi> of thoſe over whom He ruleth.) Now what thoſe generall Laws are, it is well known; As for example This God hath ſaid. <hi>He that ſheds mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed, Gen</hi> 9 6. And <hi>He that blaſphemes the Name of the</hi> Lord, <hi>ſhall ſurely be put to death.</hi> Levit. 24 16. And again <hi>If thy brother, the ſon of thy mother, or thy ſon, or thy daughter, or the wife of thy boſome, or thy friend, which is as thine own ſoule,</hi> (the King himſelf may be within the compaſſe of theſe or moſt of theſe relations, as the caſe is put) <hi>intice thee ſecretly, ſaying, let us goe and ſerve other gods, which thou haſt not known, thou nor thy fathers, thou ſhalt not conſent not him, nor hearken unto him, neither ſhall thine eye pitty him neither ſhalt thou ſpare neither ſhalt thou conceal him but thou ſhalt ſurely kill him thine hand ſhal be firſt upon him to put him to death; and afterwards the hand of all the people and thou ſhalt ſtone him with ſtones that he dye Deut.</hi> 13.6 &amp;c. In which words the Spirit of God plainly ſhews, that in this caſe, the greateſt and neareſt relation of friendſhip love and duty, that we can owe to any whatſoever they be, of what dignity or degree ſoever ſhould not make us deſiſt from the execution of Juſtice. Theſe things are ſpoken you ſee without the leaſt exception that may be, that in caſe the Rulers or the King ſhould do thus, that the like ſhould not be done unto them: but God requires that Equity and Juſtice be done alike upon all without reſpect of perſons; as we well know that this is the charge that God hath given <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.19. <hi>Thou ſhalt not wreſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thou ſhalt not reſpect perſons.</hi> Where God ſhews thus much unto us, that to reſpect the perſons of any in matter of Judgement, or Juſtice, is to wreſt Juſtice, and to goe aſide from that which is right. God will have equall and impartiall judgement ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred alike unto all: And the reaſon hereof is given by the Holyghoſt in the place before ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed. <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.11. <hi>That all Iſrael may heare and feare and doe no more any ſuch wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe.</hi> Now there is none that will deny, but that Kings by nature are as bad as any, and are ſubject to be worſe then any others, by reaſon of thoſe Flatterers and evill Counſellours, that uſually are about them, as we may ſee in the examples of <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24 17. and of <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron</hi> 10.8 &amp;c. ſhould it be ſo then that there were no Laws in force binding unto them as well as unto Us, and examples of true and equall Juſtice made upon them as well as upon others, it were the very next way to open a gappe to all Kings and Princes to all manner of wickedneſſe and licentiouſnes, and to make them Tyrants that otherwiſe would be good and gracious towards their People. Wheras this would be a very good meanes to keep Kings in as well as others, from running into ſuch extravagant courſes to the diſhonour of God, and the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their people as uſually they are wont to doe; unleſſe we will ſay that God hath given unto Kings and Princes a diſpenſation above all others, to run headlong unto Hell without controule. They that teach ſuch Doctrine by this now it appeares what friends they are unto them whatſoever they may pretend, who would make Kings of all others the moſt <hi>miſerable,</hi> by aſcribing unto them an unreſtrained liberty to all wickedneſſe whatſoever, to their deſtruction.</p>
            <p>But here comes in another Objection, for will ſome ſay againe, <hi>Kings are Gods anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:</hi> therfore men may not queſtion them much leſſe may they touch their lives what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever their actions be: And thus much ſaith David concerning <hi>Saul,</hi> who was <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> though he were a wicked King and his enemy that ſought his life; and that for no juſt cauſe neither; yet when David had an opportun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty to ſlay him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24 6. he ſpeaks thus, <hi>The Lord forbid that I ſhould doe this thing unto my Maſter the Lords anointed,
<pb facs="tcp:156215:5"/>to ſtretch forth mine hand againſt him, ſeeing he is the anointed of the Lord.</hi> So againe, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.9. <hi>Who can ſtretch forth his hand againſt the Lords anointed and be guiltleſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, <hi>David</hi> was a private man (notwithſtanding he was <hi>Sauls</hi> ſucceſſor by Gods appointment to the Crowne) and ſo had no warrant to doe ſuch a thing as this, as to take away the life of <hi>Saul</hi> the King, though hee had done him, or ſhould ſeeke to doe him never ſo much harm. For in a caſe farre Inferiour to this, wee know that if a private man be a Thiefe, and by Law is condemned to die, yet no man may lay vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent hands upon him to take away his life, but onely in a Legall way, and by the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner that is by authority appointed for this purpoſe, if any man ſhould, hee would be accounted a murtherer for ſo doing, and bee liable to ſuffer the Law in that caſe provided. So then if this cannot bee juſtifiable upon a private perſon condemned by Law, much leſſe then upon a publike perſon, eſpecially ſuch a one as a King is, and uncondemned too. Therfore in this caſe had <hi>David</hi> taken away <hi>Sauls</hi> life, who was then King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he had bin much to blame, and had ſinned exceedingly in the ſight of God, wherfore <hi>David</hi> would not doe it.</p>
            <p>But we doe not know what <hi>David</hi> would have done, or what he might have done, in caſe <hi>Saul</hi> ſhould forceibly have come upon him to have taken away his life, in his own juſt defence for his own ſafety and preſervation: for elſe for what end had <hi>David</hi> thoſe 600. men with him? Surely it will be anſwered, and I beleeve the moſt malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant among them all will not deny it, that he had them for his Defence; was it ſo? Then truly I think that they that will defend themſelvs, by Arms and armed men, muſt needs offend, when they are offended. For this is a meere conceipt that even very chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren will be ready to laugh at, to ſay that when a mans enemy comes againſt him to doe him a miſchief he muſt only defend himſelfe, but muſt not ſtrike againe. For how is this poſſible, for a man to defend himſelfe from his enemy, and yet not offend his enemy?</p>
            <p>Then for aſmuch as <hi>Kings</hi> are call'd <hi>the anointed of the Lord;</hi> they are ſo call'd in two reſpects. Firſt either in regard of the Anointing Oyle that was powred upon them, by the performance of which Ceremonie they were inaugurized into their Functions and Offices. Or elſe, in regard of that authority, which by their people they are elected unto, whereby they become Gods Deputies and Vicegerents here on earth, in ruling and governing of his people.</p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe, in aſmuch as <hi>Kings</hi> are call'd <hi>the anointed of the Lord,</hi> becauſe of the Anointing Oyle that was powred upon them, by the performance of which Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony they were inaugurized into their Functions, whereof ſome there were that God did in a more eſpeciall manner thus inſtitute and ordaine, even by His own immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate appointment, as to wit <hi>Saul, David, Solomon, Iehu,</hi> and <hi>Hazael,</hi> whom he commanded <hi>Elijah</hi> to Anoynt <hi>King</hi> over <hi>Syria.</hi> Yet I ſee no ground, nor reaſon, why even theſe ſhould not be reſponſall to the Lawes and to their <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> for their Actions. For I do not perceive that God did any whit hereby exempt them from the obſervance of his Laws, either Actively or paſſively. If not, then ſurely they that would attribute thus much unto them, doe exalt and ſet them above the Laws and Commandements of God (for you muſt underſtand that the judiciall Laws in thoſe times, whereby God would have his people to bee governed, were immediately ordained of God; as well as any other Laws whatſoever) which therfore for my own part I conceive to be no leſſe then blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy; at leaſt I am ſure it is a high contempt of Gods ordinance. Wherfore now (with ſubmiſſion to better judgements) wheras it is ſaid, <hi>Who can ſtretch forth his hand
<pb facs="tcp:156215:6"/>againſt the Lords anointed and be guitleſſe,</hi> I ſuppoſe this to be the meaning of it; That this is a thing not to be raſhly or unadviſedly done by any, and that it belongs to none but to the Magiſtrates only, and that in a legall way, having herein an awfull and reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall regard of the Commandement of God.</p>
            <p>Yet further I will not deny but that it may probably be, that there may be ſomwhat extraordinary in the caſe of theſe 5 Kings before mentioned, their perſons being of Gods immediate choice, and by his eſpeciall appointment inducted into that Function, as the rather it ſeems ſo to be, becauſe this term of the <hi>Lords anointed,</hi> I find it applyed in Scripture to no King elſe, that was anointed with Oyle, but only theſe, though we read of divers Kings elſe beſides theſe, that were anointed with Oyle.</p>
            <p>Then for the other, in that Kings are called <hi>Gods anointed</hi> with reſpect to the <hi>authority,</hi> which by their people they are elected unto, whereby they become Gods Deputies and Vicegerents here on earth, in ruling and governing of his people, Thus, and no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then thus are our Kings call'd the Anointed of the Lord; Now as much as this is proper and belonging to other Rulers as well as to Kings, to be called Gods Deputies and Vicegerents, and therefore it is that they, as I ſhewed before, are cal'd Gods as well as Kings, which little is applyed unto them, in this regard, becauſe they repreſent the place of God, and have his Image ſtamped upon them in a more eſpeciall manner, by meanes of that authority that God, by the conſent of his people hath conferred upon them for their good: From hence therefore neither doe I ſee any ground, why Kings ſhould not be accountable for their actions. For if ſo be that they are not accountable in this regard becauſe they are Gods Deputies and Vicegerents, why then I ſay, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Rulers, nor Magiſtrates beſides, becauſe they are Gods Vicegerents as well as Kings? The which, I thinke there are none will be ſo ſimple as to affirme.</p>
            <p>So now by what hath been ſaid, we ſee that even Kings in a legall way may bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, neither do we want examples among our ſelves of this kind and yet it is thought no grievance or unlawfull thing, or unbeſeeming the profeſſion of good Chriſtians, as ſome doe ſay. For it is not manifeſt that the King himſelfe is impleaded by his owne Subjects, and hath many times tryalls at Law with them at the Kings bench, and is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times too overthrowne: And if this be done in ſlighter matters, then certainely much more it ought to be done in matters, of farre greater weight and conſequence, as in caſes of oppreſſion, Tyranny, or Deſtruction of his People.</p>
            <p>But here againe ſay they, ſhould wee grant you this, that other Kings may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, as you have declared, and may Legally bee accountable for their actions, yet the caſe is not alike betweene other Kings and ours of <hi>England,</hi> for as much as they have their right to the Crown by Conqueſt, as is evident by <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour, whoſe Succeſſors they are, and therefore there is no other way for us now, but either to obey what they command us, or elſe to ſubmit our ſelves to ſuffer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It goes beyond my apprehenſion to coneive, how this kind of arguing can hold good, and I do admire upon what ground it ſhould be built. But beſides it is not here amiſſe, to take notice of the baſeneſſe and ſervility of the ſpirits of theſe men, who can be ſo well content to argue themſelves into a very vaſſalage and ſlavery: Therfore for ſatisfaction in this point as well as in the reſt, wee muſt take notice that there is a two fold conqueſt; one is Abſolute, and the other is Conditionall. For the firſt of theſe, will they affirme it, that we are abſolutely conquered, and ſo overcom by an altogether over-ruling and Tyrannicall power, that our Lives, Perſons and Eſtates lie at the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Conqueror, all that ever we have being at his will and pleaſure, that hee may
<pb facs="tcp:156215:6"/>make a prey of them how he liſt, and when he liſt; without any bonds or ties at all on his part, towards his people, but that by vertue of the Conqueſt, we are wholly become his Vaſſalls and ſlaves: I ſay in this caſe a people may by force of Armes, nay they are bound to doe it (for as much as all people ought both by the Law of God and nature to provide for their owne welfare and ſalvation) when they have a fit and convenient op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, and ſtrength ſufficient, to reſcue themſelves from under the power of ſuch a Tyranny, and free themſelves from ſuch a Yoake, though it ſhould bee even with the perſonall deſtruction of thoſe Kings, that ſhould uſurpe ſuch a power over them. And I prove it clearely by the examples of the people of God in the times of the <hi>Iudges,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the Spirit of God; as, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 3 8. Iſrael there rebelled againſt the Lord, by turning unto Idolls, whereupon it is ſaid, <hi>the anger of the Lord was hot againſt Iſrael, and he ſold them into the hands of</hi> Cuſhan Riſhathaim <hi>King of</hi> Meſopotamia, <hi>and the Children of Iſrael ſerved</hi> Cuſhon Riſhathaim <hi>eight yeeres</hi> (that is to ſay, they ſerved him in a ſervile ſlaviſh way) then it followes, <hi>that the Children of Iſraell cryed unto the Lord, and the Lord rayſed up a deliverer unto the Children of Iſrael, who delivered them, even</hi> Othniel <hi>the brother of</hi> Kenaz, Kalebs <hi>younger brother, and the ſpirit of the Lord came up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n him, and he judged Iſrael, and went out to warre, and the Lord delivered</hi> Cuſhan Riſhathaim, <hi>into his hand, and his hand prevailed againſt</hi> Cuſhan Riſhathaim, <hi>and ſo the Land had reſt</hi> 40 <hi>Yeeres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which words you ſee, that the people of God by force of Armes were violently overcome, and kept powerfully under a Tyranny, for the ſpace of eight yeeres but ſee when God had raiſed up unto them a deliverer, that is to ſay, one that would ſtand up in defence of them againſt the King of <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> who had them under, and they now had a convenient opportunity to redeeme themſelves from under this Tyranny, they take it; and by force of Armes recover their liberty againe. It is needleſſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in any more particulars at large, I will therefore onely point out the ſeverall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that for your better ſatisfaction you may read them at your leaſure. The enſuing Story doth manifeſtly prove it beginning at the 12. <hi>verſe,</hi> &amp;c. ſo againe, <hi>Iudges</hi> 4. the whole Chapter is a Story to this purpoſe: This is cleare alſo in the example of <hi>Gideon, who delivered Iſrael from the hand of the</hi> Midianites, the Story is in the 6. and 7. Chap. of <hi>Iudges.</hi> It is cleare alſo by the example of <hi>Ieptha, who delivered Iſrael from the hand of the</hi> Ammonites <hi>Iudges</hi> the 19. and 11. <hi>Chapters.</hi> So much in briefe may be ſaid concerning abſolute Conqueſt. And now I hope they will take heed, how they ſay, we were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely conquered. Then for the other, and that is Conditionall Conqueſt. So ſay they we were Conquered, and it is not denyed: That is to ſay; when <hi>William</hi> the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour invaded the Land, we were content to ſubmit our ſelves unto him, (for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of blood ſhed and deſtruction, that otherwiſe might have enſued) to ſerve him as our Liege Lord, and Soveraigne, ſo that he would promiſe to govern us, according to theſe and theſe Laws and Cuſtomes, to which covenant hee conſented, as all the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have done ſince. And ſo we are become not his ſlaves to be deſtroyed at his pleaſure, but his Subjects, having ſworne him and his Succeſſours Allegiance upon theſe conditions. If this be ſo; then here we plainely ſee, we are not bound to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Kings will and pleaſure, in all his commands, but onely ſo farre forth as hee commands according to his Laws, which is the condition upon which we ſweare him Allegiance, and become his Subjects. Therefore if the conditions of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant be broke, and inſtead of governing his people by his Lawes, he rules them as hee liſt, according to his will and pleaſure; is it not manifeſt, that the King doth abſolve his Subjects from their Allegiance, nor are they any longer, legally bound to obey
<pb facs="tcp:156215:7"/>him. For this every one knowes, that when the condition, whereby the Covenant is tied to each partie, is broken, the Covenant it ſelfe by vertue thereof is quite diſſolved, or at leaſt diſſolvable at the parties pleaſure with whom the Covenant was made. By this it appeares that the King is as much bound to the Subjects as the Subjects to the King, and that in this caſe the Subjects may make lawfull reſiſtance to recover their undoubted Liberties and Priviledges, and yet not bee termed Rebells againſt their Prince. For none but they only can be called or eſteemed ſuch, as violate their oathes of Allegiance, which we do not, if the King break with us his Covenant, wherby he hath bound himſelfe to us and upon performance whereof we ſweare him Allegiance.</p>
            <p>But now beſides all that hath bin ſaid, let us a little look into the foul abſurdities that follow upon this tenent, that people muſt ſo ſubmit themſelves unto their Kings, as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to obey their commands, though never ſo unlawfull, or elſe to ſuffer whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they ſhall inflict upon them, and not to take up defenſive Armes againſt them: but in caſe their Kings come againſt them in a hoſtile manner ſeeking their deſtruction; all that they muſt doe ſay they, is to runne away from them. But, ſay they doe ſo, they may ſo follow and perſue their people, or incompaſſe them in that they can be able to runne no further, ſo that then they muſt either perforce ſtand upon their defence, or ſubmit themſelves unto their mercy. Why? I ſay they, ſo they muſt, all the weapons they muſt uſe in this caſe are prayers and teares. So that then, if <hi>Nero</hi> like they ſhould wiſh that the whole body of their people were but one necke, that hee might cut them off at one blow, they muſt as we ſay, lay their necks upon the block, and ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to their owne deſtruction. And ſo now conſequently it follows, be their <hi>Kings</hi> never ſo great Tyrants, not onely over their bodies, but over their ſoules too (as the caſe may be, they may ſet up Popery and Idolatry in their Kingdomes, as the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah</hi> did: nay if they will, bring in very Heatheniſme, and what not, utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depriving their people of all the outward happineſſe, and comfort of their lives, and alſo as much as in them lies, proſtituting their ſoules to utter ruine, by denying them the meanes of their ſalvation) yet they may not doe any thing in this caſe to help them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs by way of juſt defence or Legall Juſtice. If this be ſo, then indeed we are behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding only to the Kings good nature, for every thing that we have and do enjoy, and not at all unto the Laws, and that will proove good doctrine that hath not long ſince bin ſo freely taught among us, That our lives, our Liberties, our Eſtates, our Wives and our Children, and all we have, are at the Kings mercy, and that wee doe injoy any of theſe, it is of his meer favor and bounty towards us: And then what need at all is there of any Laws, or why ſhould the Parliament trouble themſelvs to make any more Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes or Ordinances, wherby to govern us? the which how ridiculous it is, and how abominably falſe, and contrary to Gods word, you have already heard.</p>
            <p>It will not be improper for this diſcourſe to look a little into the caſe and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which wicked King <hi>Ahaz</hi> brought his people into by his abominable Idolatry which he eſtabliſhed in the land, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.3. It is ſaid, <hi>He burnt incenſe in the valley of the ſon of Hinnom, and burnt his children in the fire, after the abominations of the heathen, whom the Lord caſt out before the children of Iſrael. He ſacrificed alſo and burnt incenſe in the high places, and on hills, and under every green tree: wherfore the Lord his God,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>delivered him into the hand of the King of Syria, and they ſmote him</hi> (that is to ſay, his people) <hi>and carryed away a great multitude of them captive, and brought them to Damaſcus; and he was alſo delivered into the hand of the King of Iſrael, who ſmote him with a great ſlaughter. For Peca the ſonne of Remaliah ſlew in Iudah</hi> 12000. <hi>in one day, which were all valiant men:</hi> and the reaſon follows,
<pb facs="tcp:156215:7"/>
               <hi>becauſe they had forſaken the Lord God of their fathers.</hi> By whoſe meanes was this that they had done it, was it not by reaſon of their Idolatrous King <hi>Ahaz?</hi> Then in the 8. verſe, <hi>the children of Iſrael carryed away captive of them</hi> 200000. <hi>women, ſons and daughters, and took alſo away much ſpoile from them, and brought the ſpoile to Samaria.</hi> Againe in the 16. verſe, <hi>Ahaz ſends to the King of Syria to help him againſt the Edomites that came and ſmote Iudah, who carryed them away captive; the Philiſtims alſo had invaded the Cities of the low Countries, and of the ſouth of Iudah, and had taken divers Townes from them,</hi> as there they are reckoned up, <hi>and dwelt there:</hi> for it is ſaid, <hi>The Lord brought Iudah low becauſe of Ahaz King of Iſrael, for he had made Iudah naked, and tranſgreſſed ſore againſt the Lord.</hi> So in the 20. verſe againe it is ſaid, <hi>That Tilgath Pilnezer, King of Aſſyria came unto him, and diſtreſſed him, but ſtrengthned him not, for Ahaz took a portion out of the houſe of the Lord, and out of the houſe of the King, and of the Princes, and gave it unto the King of Aſſyria, but he helped him not.</hi> There you ſee was alſo ſo much of the treaſure of the land loſt. Again it is ſaid, <hi>that in the time of his diſtreſſe he did treſpaſſe yet more againſt the Lord.</hi> (This is that King <hi>Ahaz,</hi>) <hi>for he ſacrificed unto the Gods of Damaſcus which ſmote him:</hi> and he ſaid, <hi>becauſe the Gods of the Kings of Syria helpe them, therfore will I ſacrifice to them, that they may help me:</hi> but they were the ruine of him, and of all <hi>Iſrael.</hi> To this lamentable condition was <hi>Iſrael</hi> now brought, through the wickedneſſe of this man. How much better had it bin for them to have executed the judgement of the Lord upon him, who in his moſt juſt and righteous Law required, <hi>that all Idolaters,</hi> without reſpect of perſons, <hi>ſhould be deſtroyed;</hi> and had given more then an ordinary charge concerning this particular, then, by the neglect of the execution of <hi>juſtice,</hi> to have brought themſelvs to that miſerable condition wherin they were, both in reſpect of their ſoules and bodies. And who knows whether God might not lay the heavier load upon them, for this their contempt, in not obeying his Commandement; whereas if ſo be they had done this, they might ſtill have continued in the favour of God, and bin a bleſſed and renowned people as their predeceſſours were.</p>
            <p>But if it ſhall be ſaid, Why did they not execute <hi>juſtice</hi> in this kind upon him, and other their Idolatrous Kings, it ſeems there was ſomwhat more then ordinary in it, in that it was omitted?</p>
            <p>I anſwer. It was no marvaile they did neglect the execution of <hi>juſtice</hi> in this regard upon their Kings, when as they were ſo careleſſe to doe it upon common and private perſons: for we never read that ever there was ſo much as any one perſon, after they were come into the promiſed poſſeſſion of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> that they did put to death for their Idolatry, of what kind or condition ſoever they were: and if this were thus o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted upon perſons of ordinary and mean ranke and qualitie, how ſhould it be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that it ſhould be executed upon their Kings.</p>
            <p>Yet beſides all this that hath bin ſaid, to ſhew the unreaſonableneſſe and falſeneſſe of this Depoſition <hi>(that Kings are unaccountable for their actions, and may not be reſiſted, though they doe thoſe things that are never ſo diſhonourable to God, and prejudiciall and hurtfull to their Subjects)</hi> there may ſomwhat more be ſaid with reference to the Wiſdome of God. For how is it poſſible to be imagined, that He who is ſo <hi>infinitely wiſe</hi> (having in His <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable underſtanding</hi> appointed Government as the only meanes for his peoples hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and well being here on earth, ſhould leave His people in ſuch a condition, that if ſo be the meanes and inſtruments, which he hath ordained for their good, ſhould riſe up againſt them to their <hi>deſtruction,</hi> they ſhould have no power leſt them to help themſelvs, nor meanes to provide for their own ſafety, but muſt be faine to ſubmit themſelvs to their wills and pleaſures. How doth this exceedingly reflect upon the Wiſdome and
<pb facs="tcp:156215:8"/>Providence of God; and is it not manifeſt and apparent that Gods ends and intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Government are hereby quite fruſtrated and void, ſo as that, that which he hath appointed for his peoples greateſt benefit and ſecurity, ſhould turn to their greateſt hurt and miſchief. And this were the next way, inſtead of making God the <hi>authour of peace,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14 33. to make him the chiefeſt authour of all diſorder and confuſion. For let any man judge that hath but the ordinary underſtanding of a man, if this be not occaſion ſufficient to make even the beſt of Kings (if God doe not give them more then an ordinary meaſure of his Grace) to become Tyrants, and to live as they liſt, when they are perſwaded that they may doe what they liſt, and none may controule them.</p>
            <p>Therfore for the more full clearing of that which hath bin already ſaid, it will not be amiſſe to ſearch a little narrowly into the meaning of that place, <hi>Rom,</hi> 13.1 &amp;c. and ſo to acquaint our ſelves what that <hi>power</hi> is, which the Apoſtle there calls <hi>the ordinance of God, Let every ſoule be ſubject unto the higher powers, for there is no power but of God, the powers that be are ordain'd of God.</hi> They are Magiſtrates that are here meant by theſe <hi>powers,</hi> and theſe <hi>powers</hi> the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>are of God.</hi> Now I aske, did ever God give a <hi>power</hi> unto any for the deſtruction of his people, and of thoſe that are committed to their charge? is this the Ordinance of God for Kings and Rulers to ſeek the undoing and ruine of their people? Surely no. God did appoint them for his peoples good, as before was ſhewed; and thus much alſo the Apoſtle declares to us here in the words following, verſe 3. <hi>Rulers are not a terrour to good works, but to the evill. Wilt thou not be afraid of the power? doe that which is good and thou ſhalt have praiſe of the ſame for he is the miniſter of God to thee for good,</hi> &amp;c. (Here by the way this ſhews unto us, that the acts of Kings for the good of their people, are not acts of Grace, as ſome flatterers would make them, but they are acts of Dutie, which God requires from them towards their people.)</p>
            <p>And beſides, let us have a reſpect unto Kings and Governours too, as they are a <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ordinance,</hi> as the Apoſtle calls them, as you heard before, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. &amp;c. Did ever the people who elected them, give them any ſuch power as to rule them according to their <hi>wills</hi> and <hi>pleaſures?</hi> If they have, what made they thoſe good Laws for, according to which they Covenanted for to govern them? And therfore as the Apoſtle before ſaith, <hi>they are the ordinance of God</hi> with reſpect to their peoples good; ſo here the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>they are the ordinance of man</hi> with reſpect to the ſame: For ſo he ſaith, <hi>Submit your ſelves to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whether unto the King as ſupreme, or unto Governours, as they that are ſent by him;</hi> What for? Or to what end? (ſurely not for their deſtruction, but to be inſtruments of their well being, for ſo it followes) <hi>for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of evill doers, and for the praiſe of them that doe well.</hi> Therfore hence I ſay, If Kings who are Ordained by God, and Choſen by Men, for this <hi>end,</hi> to be inſtruments of <hi>good</hi> to their People, doe contrarily abuſe their Authority, wherewithall they are intruſted both by God and Man, to the <hi>hurt</hi> and <hi>deſtruction</hi> of their People: if in this caſe the People to preſerve themſelvs doe ſtand upon their own Defence, and take up Armes for their own <hi>protection,</hi> they do not <hi>reſiſt the ordinance of</hi> God, nor come within the reach of the Apoſtles cenſure, as thoſe that for ſo doing <hi>ſhall receive damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is one thing yet more that I have to ſay concerning the Unlimited Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; and ſo I ſhall finiſh this Diſcourſe; and that is, What good can there come by aſcribing ſuch a Power? For every circumſtance in point of Government muſt have reſpect unto ſome <hi>good</hi> or other, either for the <hi>glory of</hi> God, or for the <hi>benefit of the People:</hi> if ſo be that they conduce not to theſe ends, they are utterly to be rejected, as ſinfull and obnoxious. For God never gave Magiſtrates any ſuch <hi>power,</hi> as to be unlimitable in
<pb facs="tcp:156215:8"/>breaking his Commandements; or to become <hi>terrible</hi> and dreadfull to their People: but this He requires, that they eſpecially, whom He and His People have truſted with <hi>power</hi> and <hi>Magiſtracie,</hi> ſhould by their example honour God in a holy and godly <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,</hi> and be <hi>comfortable</hi> and <hi>profitable</hi> to their <hi>People,</hi> through their <hi>pious, peaceable,</hi> and <hi>Religious government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how or which way doth it appear that the <hi>unlimited Prerogative</hi> hath, or can have reſpect to any ſuch ends: nay <hi>reaſon</hi> tells us the contrary; and We have learned aſmuch by the beſt of Schoolmaſters, to wit, <hi>experience;</hi> And if the Spirit of God ſay true, a great deale of evill and miſchief may come by it, but no good at all as ever I could read. Thus much we may perceive, if we will look into that place in the 17. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. where the Spirit of God ſpeaking concerning the King, when he ſhall come to ſit upon the Throne of his Kingdome, <hi>He ſhall write</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a coppie of this Law in a Booke, out of that which is before the Prieſts the Levites, and it ſhall be with him; and he ſhall read therein all the dayes of his life, that he may learne to feare the Lord his God, to keep all the words of this law, and theſe Statutes to do them.</hi> Here we ſee the rule, which God would have Kings apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unto in governing of their People, but here is no grant or Charter that God at all hath given them, to rule them according to their <hi>wills</hi> and <hi>pleaſures;</hi> and he binds them within the compaſſe of His Law. And it cannot be denied but that theſe Statutes and Commandements of God before ſpoken of, require <hi>paſsive</hi> as well as <hi>active</hi> Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. For what is here ſaid unto Kings, is oftentimes in this Book, and elſe where, ſaid unto the People; and I beleeve there is none will ſay, but that they are required therby to obey in both kinds: why not Kings then as well as others, for here is no exception. Nay the Spirit of God here gives us a ſufficient reaſon, that they ought ſo to doe, in the words following, for ſo it is ſaid, <hi>leaſt his heart be lifted up above his brethren.</hi> He foreſaw what miſchief would come of it, if Kings ſhould have any ſuch Unlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Power allowed them. And indeed how can it otherwiſe be, but they muſt needs exceedingly ſwell with Pride, when they ſhall be made like God, ſubject to no Laws. And what doe they elſe, that aſcribe ſuch a <hi>power</hi> unto them, as that they are no waies <hi>accountable,</hi> or <hi>puniſhable</hi> for any <hi>actions</hi> that they doe? Is not this the very next way to cauſe them to deſpiſe and <hi>trample</hi> their People under their feet, as if they were ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly beneath them (though in truth they be the ſame, and equall with them, in reſpect of their <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>being,</hi> (therfore the Spirit of God here calls them their <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren</hi>) the difference only lying in their <hi>power</hi> and <hi>Magiſtracie</hi>) and to make them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get themſelves and their humane condition, as if they were a degree above Men, by exalting them above all Laws, as if by vertue of their place and Dignitie, their very nature were changed into the Divine.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, it is further worth the marking, what other evill conſequence will be readie to follow, if ſuch a <hi>power,</hi> as is ſaid before, ſhould be aſcribed Therfore it is ſaid in the next words <hi>(that he turne not aſide from the Commandement, to the right hand or to the left)</hi> as who ſhould ſay to give Kings ſuch a <hi>power</hi> as is Unlimited and diſreſponſable, it is the very next way to cauſe them to <hi>preſume</hi> and take <hi>liberty</hi> to themſelves, how they liſt and when they liſt to break the Commandements of God and to caſt his Precepts behind their backs.</p>
            <p>Here we ſee now the evill that comes by this Prerogative, I would any one could ſhew me what that good is that doth from it ariſe; or where in all the Scripture it is ſaid, <hi>that Kings ſhall not be accountable for what they doe.</hi> I perſwade my ſelfe that it will be a taske too hard for any man to undertake.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:156215:9"/>
            <p>By this it appeares, what Enemies they are to the Common-wealth, and what a deale of miſchief they doe, that teach ſuch Doctrine as Kings Unlimited Power, and how abominable they muſt needs be both in the ſight of God and Men, that teach men to erre from Gods Commandements; and to conclude all in a word, I may here ſay to ſuch as our Saviour doth, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall break one of the leaſt of theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and ſhall teach men ſo to doe, ſhall be call'd the leaſt in the Kingdome of heaven.</hi> And here alſo I may well remember them of the words of that prediction of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.11. which are truly verified in theſe men. <hi>God ſhall ſend them ſtrong Deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that they may beleeve a lye, that all they might be damned that beleeve not the truth, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I doe not much queſtion but that this paper may light of thoſe that will not ſpare to lay Cenſure hard enough upon it; and it is not unlikely but it may ſuffer under that terrible name of Treaſon; yet I ſay it would be well for them before they ſhoot their bolt, to conſider wiſely with themſelves what they doe leaſt otherwiſe they prove to be ſuch as fall foule upon the Truth of God, and ſo be found to be ſuch as fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Him, which if they doe, let themſelves judge how it is like to be with them. But let it be as it will, yet the comfort is, it is not the firſt time that Truth hath ſuffer'd under as bad a Cenſure as this can be: and let them that are enemies to this Truth doe what they can, yet let me tell them that Truth is ſtrong, and ſhall prevaile; and that howſoever it may be blamed by thoſe that <hi>hate</hi> it, yet it ſhall never be <hi>aſhamed.</hi> And as all Truth ought to be known, ſo eſpeciallie every Truth in its chiefeſt time and ſeaſon: for as the Wiſe man ſaith, <hi>Pro.</hi> 25.11. <hi>A word ſpoken in due ſeaſon, is like apples of gold in pictures of ſilver,</hi> then it is moſt like to do good, and then moſt acceptable and delightfull. I have ſpoken a few words upon this theame the rather, that hereby at leaſt I might provoke thoſe of better judgements, and are able to ſay farre more of this point then my ſelfe, according to the neceſſitie of the times to ſpeak in this behalfe, if they be lovers of their King, of the Truth, and of their Countrie: And ſo I commend it to the bleſſing of GOD.</p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
